Guide to the Gregory Corso Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Writings, 1949-1996 and Undated
  - Poems-- by Corso
    - Miscellaneous Poems
      - Notebooks
        - 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
        - Undated, (4 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 8 to 11)
  - Poems-- by Others
    - Heliczer, Piero--The Soap Opera circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      (copy, with manuscript corrections)
    - Hollander, John-- "Another for Gregory," undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Olsen, Charles-- "A Maximus Written to Answer Allen Ginsberg and Gregory Corso," undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Schenck, Stephen-- "Sweety-bar in time and space…," undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
      (carbon copy with corrections)
- Series IV: Artwork, 1954-1977 and Undated
  This series contains artwork, mostly sketches and drawings done by Corso, as well as a very few items created by others. There are some larger format items, including oil paintings done by Corso and a large oil portrait of the poet in this series as well. The Robert LaVigne Papers contain some sketches of LaVigne done by Corso, as well as portraits of Corso by LaVigne and Jack Kerouac.
  - Abraham and His Tribe Leaving Ur, (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - [Animals], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - [Angel], (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - [Angel], (pencil and wash) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - [Angel and stamped portrait of Corso] (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - [Angel with trumpet], (charcoal sketch) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - [Birds], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - [Birds], pen and ink (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - [Black and red design], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - [Black, red, and green sketch], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - [Branch and ivory seal], (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 11)
    (signed Nunzio)
  - A China Man and Family, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Cityscape [Athenian Agora?], (oil on wood) (Box 14-E-6)
  - [Collage],1974 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Contemporary Glyph, (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - [Cowboy and Horse], (ink sketch) (Box 14-E-6)
  - Cunt with Testicles, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - [Demonic signature], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - [Design], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - [Eagle], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - [Face], (ballpoint pen) (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - [Face], (pen and ink); (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 20 to 21)
  - [Face and plant], (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - [Face in brown ink], ink wash) (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - A Good Boy!, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Harry Smith, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - [Head of Christ], (crayon drawing) (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Judy Chicago, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - [Man and duck], (pen and ink on cocktail napkin) (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - [Mechanical design], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Milton, (pencil sketch) (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - [Musician], (ink sketch) (Box 7)
  - [Nine figures], (pen and ink); (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 31 to 32)
  - On a Cave Wall at Trois Freres Shaman with Antler Headgear, (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Onomatopoeia, (pencil sketch) (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Percy B. Shelley, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Portrait of A. Ginsberg, Salem, MA, 1973; (oil on canvas board) (Box 14-E-6)
  - Portrait of Peggy Biderman, (pencil drawing) (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - The Rebel, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - [Renaissance prince], (pencil and pastel) (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - [Seal], (sketch) (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - [Self-portrait], (ink sketch) (Box 14-E-6)
  - Self-portrait,1962 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - [Seven figures] Milan,1965 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - [Six figures], (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - [Sketches on graph paper],1977 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    (inscribed to Peggy Biderman)
  - The Sorrow of Saturn, (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Spring Ram and Lamb, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - [Stylized figure], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - [Three figures], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - [Three Figures] and [Four Knights in Armor], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - To the Most Beautiful Pegasus, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - [Tree Stump], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - [Trees and sun] and [Face] (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - [Two figures and a cat] (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - [Two figures holding the world] (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - [Two figures in one], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - [Untitled], (paint on paper) (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - [Vase, flowers and books], (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Weeping Spring, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Where Did Everyone Go?, (pen and ink) (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Wilde, (ink sketch) (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Painting of Gregory Corso-- by G. Waldas, 1954, (oil on cardboard) (Box 14-E-6)
  - Sketch of Gregory Corso-- by Larry Rivers (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbooks
    - 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      (contains drawings and poetry)
    - March, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      (contains drawings and paintings)
    - Undated, (2 volumes) (Box 8, Folder 5 to 6)
- Series V: Printed Material, 1958-1972
  The printed material series includes editions of Corso's printed work, including work published in literary journals or magazines as well as anthologies and books of Corso's poetry in translation. Additionally, the series contains several books, journals, and independent literary magazines from Corso's collection including a large number that originally belonged to the San Francisco poet Lenore Kandel. These literary magazines are of particular interest to the researcher studying San Francisco's underground poetry scene in the 1950s and 1960s.
  - Anthologies
    - Americans Today 1969 (Box 9)
      (contains "Spontaneous Requiem for the American Indian)
    - New American Poetry, Grove Press, 1960 (Box 9)
      (includes 11 poems by Corso)
    - New Directions 1964 (Box 9)
    - Reflections on A Gift of Watermelon Pickle and Other Modern Verse 1966 (Box 9)
      (contains "Poets Hitchhiking on the Highway")
    - War Poems(contains "The Winds of Babylon") (Box 9)
  - Books of Poetry
    - Earth Egg and Unmuzzled Ox, 2nd Edition, 1974 (Box 9)
      (two copies- one inscribed to Peggy Biderman)
    - Elegiac Feelings American New Directions, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Gasoline Pocket Poets Series no. 8, City Lights, 1958 (Box 9)
    - The Happy Birthday of Death New Directions, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Long Live Man New Directions, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Translations
      - Benzina (Box 9)
        dual edition of Gasoline in both Italian and English
      - Sl Mokre More (Box 9)
        slightly abridged versions of Gasoline and Happy Birthday of Death translated into Czech, 1964
      - Zmrtvychvstanie Smrti (Box 9)
        Czech language version of Happy Birthday of Death Czech version, 1963
  - Ephemeral Printed Materials
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1967 and undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
      (includes reviews, pamphlets, literary magazines and ephemera)
    - Metropolitan Review 1971 December 14 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Recipes (Tufts University Literary Magazine), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      (contains Corso poem "By Your Wish)
  - Literary Journals
    - The Archive Spring 1971 (Box 9)
      (contains "Poem")
    - Big Table 1, Spring, 1959 (Box 9)
      (contains the complete contents of the suppressed Winter 1959 Chicago Review as well as three poems by Gregory Corso)
    - City Lights Journal no. 3, 1966 (Box 9)
      (contains "Mutation of the Spirit")
    - Jeopardy: A Magazine of Creative Arts Spring 1968 (Box 9)
    - Northwest Review Fall 1963 (Box 9)
  - Books from Corso's Library
    - Books
      - The Dark Kingdom, Kenneth Patchen, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Fertig, 1966 (Box 9)
        (inscribed to Lenore Kandel and Bill Fritz)
      - For Julessa, Bill Bathurst, 1967 (Box 9)
        (inscribed to Corso)
      - I Want You Wild and Leap, Ron Forbes and Irene Baker, 1961 (Box 9)
      - The Road to Oblivion: Poem as a Scenario, Louis W. Roddewig, 1966, 1968 (Box 9)
        (inscribed to Lenore Kandel)
      - Square Sun Square Moon: A Collection of Sweet and Sour Essays, 1967 (Box 9)
        (inscribed to Lenore Kandel and William Fritz)
      - Star River, Myron Ruderman, 1968 (Box 9)
      - Takuboku: Poems to Eat, Selected Tanka (Box 9)
      - Taylor Mead: Excerpts from the Anonymous Diary of a New York Youth, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Ubu Roi, Alfred Jarry, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Journals and Literary Magazines
      - Balls (inscribed to Bill Fritz and Lenore Kandel by Robert Branaman) (Box 9)
      - The Black Cat, November 1907 (Box 9)
      - Contact: The San Francisco Journal of New Writing, Art and Ideas no. 1, 1958 (Box 9)
      - Dedicated to All Who Helped (Box 9)
      - The Floating Bear Newsletter, 1964 (Box 9)
        (edited by Diane Di Prima)
      - The Founding Pig, Aymon de Roussy de Sales (Box 9)
      - Nexus: The San Francisco Literary Magazine, vol. 2 no.5, October, 1965 (Box 9)
      - Notes from Underground no. 11, 1966 (Box 9)
      - Or, no. 1, 1966 (Box 9)
      - Out of Sight: A Magazine of Literature, vol. 1 no. 1, 1966 (Box 9)
        (inscribed to Lenore Kandel from editor Gino Clays)
      - Residu, vol. 1 no. 1. Spring 1965 (Box 9)
      - Sun, no. 3, 1961 (Box 9)
      - The, no. 2 (Box 9)
      - Untitled Literary Magazine (Box 9)
      - Yeah, no. 5, 1962 (Box 9)
      - Zeitgeist, vol. II no. 4, 1969 (Box 9)
- Series VI: Sound Recordings, 1966 and Undated
  The sound recordings series is comprised of 5 reels of audio tape containing readings by Corso as well as his associates such as Ezra Pound, Lenore Kandel, Ken Kesey, Allen Ginsberg, and Michael McClure.
  - Corso and Ezra Pound reading at Spoleto, 1966 July 16 (2 reels) (Box 8)
  - Grogan, Ginsberg, Kesey McClure, etc. (Box 8)
  - Lenore Kandel reading "Poem for Perverts"